Joshua Reynolds Collection
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Commonplace books, notebooks, and diaries, Series II
  - Commonplace book: given to young Reynolds by his father, circa 1730-1741; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; 90 leaves; 21 x 17 cm. (Box Reynolds 33)
    Contains records copied from the family Bible and quotations from his reading. The latest date in the book is a year after Reynolds went to London to study under Thomas Hudson.
    Commonplace books; Hudson, Thomas, 1701-1779; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792
  - Commonplace book, circa 1753-1760; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; 88 leaves; 21 x 17 cm. (Box Reynolds 34)
    Contains extracts from his reading (chiefly Pope and Shakespeare) and rough drafts of projected essays on painting.
    Commonplace books; Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616; Pope, Alexander, 1688-1744; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792
  - Notebook, 1773; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; 44 leaves; 19 x 13 cm. (Box Reynolds 35)
    Lists people and houses to be seen in Paris, and pictures that he examined, chiefly those at the Hotel de Thiers that Catherine the Great was about to buy.
    This notebook is the subject of: Frederick W. Hilles, "Sir Joshua and the Hotel de Thiers," Gazette des beaux-arts (Oct. 1969): 201-210.
    Paris (France) -- Description and travel; Notebooks; Painting, European; Catherine, Empress of Russia, II, 1729-1796; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792
  - Travelling memorandum book, 1781; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; 85 leaves; 12 x 9 cm. (Box Reynolds 36)
    Brief notes made on his first trip to Brussels. Also on microfilm.
    Brussels (Belgium); Diaries; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792 -- Diaries
  - Notebook, 1781; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; 97 leaves; 23 x 21 cm. (Box Reynolds 37)
    Notes on paintings seen in Antwerp. In a pocket are business cards issued by picture dealers. Cased with Reynolds 38.
    Painting, European; Notebooks; Antwerp (Belgium) -- Description and travel
  - Diary, 1781; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; 130 leaves (2 loose leaves); 23 x 21 cm. (Box Reynolds 38)
    Inscribed: "A Painter's Journal through Flanders, Brabant, Holland, and part of Germany. June 24, 1781." Cased with Reynolds 37.
    Germany -- Description and travel; Diaries; Belgium -- Description and travel; Netherlands -- Description and travel; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792 -- Diaries
  - Notebook, 1785; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; 20 leaves; 16 x 11 cm. (Box Reynolds 39)
    Brief notes on pictures at St. Omers, Lisle, Tournay, Brussels, Mecklin, and Calais.
    Painting, European; Notebooks; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792
  - Sketchbook formerly attributed to Sir Joshua Reynolds, late 18th century; 41 leaves; 21 x 17 cm. (Box Reynolds 40)
    Sketchbook including sketches once believed to be in preparation for Mrs. Siddons as Tragic Muse.
    Sketchbooks; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792
- Writings, Series III
  - Thoughts on blindness, 1781; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; 2 pages; 32 x 20 cm. (Box Reynolds 41)
    A description in Reynolds' hand of his sensations when his sight was impaired. Including two newsprint biographies of the artist and handwritten notation: "Autograph of Sir Joshua Reynolds---of J. Waller Fleet St 1876."
    Blindness; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792
  - Fragments of Discourses, late 18th century; Northcote, James, 1746-1831; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; 3 fragments; 24 x 16 cm. and smaller (Box Reynolds 42a)
    Scraps rescued from trash by Sir Joshua's pupil James Northcote, who later became his biographer. Including several handwritten notations by James Northcote verifying the hand of Sir Joshua Reynolds. With this is cased Manuscript Fragments of Discourses and Lecture.
  - Fragments of Discourses and Lecture, late 18th century; Northcote, James, 1746-1831; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; 3 fragments; 8 x 10 cm. (Box Reynolds 42b)
    Including one notation by Northcote which verifies the hand of Reynolds. Cased with Manuscript Fragments of Discourses.
  - Draft dedication for Art of painting, 1783?; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; 2 pages; 33 x 20 cm. (Box Reynolds 43)
    Draft of a never-completed dedication to William Mason of a new edition of du Fresnoy's Art of painting, a Latin poem translated by Mason and annotated by Reynolds (published by A. Ward, 1783).
    Dufresnoy, Charles-Alphonse, 1611-1668; Mason, William, 1725-1797
  - Draft on Reynolds' collection of Old Masters, 1791?; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; 2 pages; 24 x 19 cm. (Box Reynolds 44)
    Rough draft of a portion of catalogue for Reynolds' exhibition of his collection of Old Masters in the spring of 1791. [Appears to be a draft for a paragraph which was published in the Morning Chronicle, Fri., April 22, 1791.]
    Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792
  - Notes on Pliny, 1750; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; 4 pages; 19 x 15 cm. (Box Reynolds 45)
    Notes on Melmoth's translation of Pliny's letters, made in 1750 on the trip to Italy.
    Melmoth, William, 1710?-1799; Pliny, the Younger
  - Notes on Johnson's Lives of the poets, between 1784 and 1792; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; 3 pages; 33 x 21 cm. (Box Reynolds 46)
    Notes on Johnson's Lives of the Poets, made after Johnson's death, and used when Reynolds was revising his Discourses for the collected edition. Discovered with Boswell Papers in a stable loft at Malahide Castle.
    Johnson, Samuel, 1709-1784
  - Receipt for portraits of the Marquis of Granby, 1762 January 27; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; 1 page; 34 x 23 cm. (Box Reynolds 47)
    Receipts (financial records); Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; Granby, John Manners, Marquis of, 1721-1770
- Miscellaneous, Series IV
  - "Epistle to Sir Joshua Reynolds & Co.", 1775 December; Barnard, Thomas, 1728-1806; 3 pages; 33 x 20 cm. (Box Reynolds 48)
    A reply in verse to a remark made by Johnson.
    Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; Johnson, Samuel, 1709-1784; Barnard, Thomas, 1728-1806
  - Letter to Frances Reynolds, 1781 July 21; Johnson, Samuel, 1709-1784; 2 pages; 16 x 10 cm. (Box Reynolds 49)
    Offering criticism on the writings of Frances Reynolds (sister of Joshua Reynolds).
    Correspondence; Johnson, Samuel, 1709-1784 -- Correspondence; Reynolds, Frances, 1729-1807 -- Correspondence
  - Letter to Frances Reynolds, 1783 October 1; Johnson, Samuel, 1709-1784; 1 page; 30 x 23 cm. (Box Reynolds 50)
    Complaining of illness and solitude, and speaking of the comfort of having Frances Reynolds near. Mounted verso: "I have the honour to be/Sir/Your most Obedient and/most humble Servant/Howe."
    Correspondence; Reynolds, Frances, 1729-1807 -- Correspondence; Johnson, Samuel, 1709-1784 -- Correspondence
  - Letter to Frances Reynolds, 1783 December 8; Johnson, Samuel, 1709-1784; 1 page; 22 x 12 cm. (Box Reynolds 51)
    Dinner invitation.
  - Letters to William Johnson, in India, 1781-1792; Palmer, Mary; 192 pages; 25 x 21 cm. (Box Reynolds 52)
    Series of bound letters; including handwritten descriptions of these twenty five letters by a relative of Mary Palmer (sister of Sir Joshua Reynolds), and typewritten description of the same on letterhead of Hamill & Barker, 230 North Michigan Ave., Chicago.
    Correspondence; Johnson, William, d. 1779 -- Correspondence; Palmer, Mary -- Correspondence
  - Heights of members of the Royal Academy Club, 1787 November 23; Farington, Joseph, 1747-1821; 1 page; 30 x 18 cm. (Box Reynolds 53)
    The list includes the names of 28 club members, but heights are recorded for five only: Reynolds, Sir William Chambers, John Singleton Copley, John Webber, and Ozias Humphry.
    Royal Academy of Arts (Great Britain); Farington, Joseph, 1747-1821
  - Letter (initialed "CB") to Miss Burney, at Queen's House, 1790 December 13; Burney, Charles, 1726-1814; 6 pages; 23 x 19 cm. (Box Reynolds 54)
    Letter written to his daughter, Frances, after hearing Sir Joshua Reynolds deliver his final Discourse at the Royal Academy.
    Correspondence; Burney, Fanny, 1752-1840 -- Correspondence; Burney, Charles, 1726-1814 -- Correspondence; Royal Academy of Arts (Great Britain); Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792
  - Obituary of Sir Joshua Reynolds, 1792 February 24; Burke, Edmund, 1729-1797; 4 pages; 39 x 25 cm. (Box Reynolds 55)
    Obituary written in JR's home immediately following his death. Typewritten transcription included.
    Obituaries; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792
  - Copy of speech delivered to the Royal Academy, 28 February 1792, 1792 February 28; West, Benjamin, 1738-1820; 4 pages; 25 x 20 cm. (Box Reynolds 56)
    Speech delivered to the Royal Academy at a special meeting held after Reynolds' death.
    Orations; Royal Academy of Arts (Great Britain); Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792
  - Letter to Mrs. Johnson, at Torrington, Devon, 1796 December 1; Reynolds, Frances, 1729-1807; 2 pages; 26 x 21 cm. (Box Reynolds 57a)
    Written in London. Requesting personal information and important dates in the life of their brother, Sir Joshua Reynolds, on behalf of the biographer, Edmund Malone. With this is bound Elizabeth Johnson's letter to Frances Reynolds, 4 December 1796.
    Correspondence; Malone, Edmond, 1741-1812; Reynolds, Frances, 1729-1807 -- Correspondence; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; Johnson, Elizabeth, 1721-1798 -- Correspondence
  - Letter to Edward (!sic) Malone Esq. at Queen Anne Street East, [1796] December 8; Reynolds, Frances, 1729-1807; 4 pages; 26 x 21 cm. (Box Reynolds 57b)
    Inviting Edmund Malone to call in order that he might ask further questions concerning the biography of Sir Joshua Reynolds. Cased with Frances Reynolds' letter to Mrs. Johnson, at Torrington, Devon and Elizabeth Johnson's letter to Frances Reynolds.
    Correspondence; Malone, Edmond, 1741-1812 -- Correspondence; Reynolds, Frances, 1729-1807 -- Correspondence; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792
  - Letter to Frances Reynolds, 1796 December 4; Johnson, Elizabeth, 1721-1798; 1 page; 26 x 21 cm. (Box Reynolds 57c)
    Apparently the text or first draft of a response to her sister. Additional script in same hand exists at bottom of sheet and is dated 15 December. Bound with Frances Reynolds' letter to Mrs. Johnson, at Torrington, Devon.
    Correspondence; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; Johnson, Elizabeth, 1721-1798 -- Correspondence; Malone, Edmond, 1741-1812; Reynolds, Frances, 1729-1807 -- Correspondence
  - Humorous verses, 1775?; Garrick, David, 1717-1779; 1 page; 24 x 20 cm. (Box Reynolds 58)
    Verses entitled "Merry and Wise" written when Beauclerk forgot an invitation he had extended to Reynolds, Barnard, and Garrick, probably in 1775.
    Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; Garrick, David, 1717-1779; Barnard, Thomas, 1728-1806; Beauclerk, Topham, 1739-1780 -- Correspondence
  - Manuscript copy of "Lettera scritta da Giuseppe Baretti a Luigi Siries a Firenze", 1776 January 26; 4 pages; 31 x 19 cm. (Box Reynolds 59)
    Giuseppe Pelli's copy of Baretti's printed pamphlet Baretti critical of Siries [see Reynolds 60, below].
    Pelli Bencivenni, Giuseppe, 1729-1808; Baretti, Giuseppe Marco Antonio, 1719-1789; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792
  - "Lettera scritta da Giuseppe Baretti a Luigi Siries a Firenze", 1778; Baretti, Giuseppe Marco Antonio, 1719-1789; 4 pages; 24 x 17 cm. (Box Reynolds 60)
    In this privately printed pamphlet Baretti criticizes Siries for editing and publishing Baretti's translation of the first seven of Sir Joshua Reynolds' Discourses (Delle arti del disegno. Firenze, 1778) without mentioning Baretti's name in the publication, and for altering the text. Distributed gratis throughout Italy, particularly in Tuscany (cf. Hilles, p. 54). Discussion of this pamphlet and an English translation appear in Hilles, F.W. Literary career of Sir Joshua Reynolds (1936 ed.), p. 51-59. This copy is addressed in manuscript (and was evidently mailed to) Giuseppe Pelli, director of the Royal Art Gallery in Florence.
    Correspondence; Pelli Bencivenni, Giuseppe, 1729-1808; Baretti, Giuseppe Marco Antonio, 1719-1789; Siries, Luigi, 1743-1811; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792
  - Johnson and Garrick: (Not Published). London, Printed by Nichols, Son, and Bentley...1816, Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; 15 pages; 23 x 15 cm. (Box Reynolds 61)
    "The following jeu d'esprit was written by Sir Joshua Reynolds to illustrate a remark which he made, 'That Dr. Johnson considered Garrick as his property, and would suffer anyone to praise or abuse him but himself.' In the first of these supposed dialogues, Sir Joshua himself, by high encomiums upon Garrick, is represented as drawing down upon him Johnson's censure; in the second, Mr. Gibbon, by taking the opposite side, calls forth his praise."--Title page verso.
    Johnson, Samuel, 1649-1703; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; Garrick, David, 1717-1779
  - Letter to G. Agar Ellis, 1816? April 8; Jekyll, Joseph, 1754-1837; 1 page; 12 x 10 cm. (Box Reynolds 62)
    Concerning the unpublished "Johnson and Garrick" written by Sir Joshua Reynolds. Cased with "Johnson and Garrick."
    Correspondence; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; Ellis, G. Agar -- Correspondence; Jekyll, Joseph, 1754-1837 -- Correspondence
  - Invitation to Sir Joshua Reynolds' funeral at the Royal Academy, 1792 March; 1 page; 11 x 15 cm. (Box Reynolds 63)
    Invitations; Royal Academy of Arts (Great Britain); Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792
  - Letter to Edmund Burke, Edmund Malone, and Philip Metcalfe, 1792 March 2; Macartney, George Macartney, Earl, 1737-1806; 4 pages; 23 x 19 cm. (Box Reynolds 64)
    Written from Curzon Street. Declining the invitation to Sir Joshua Reynolds' funeral.
    Correspondence; Metcalfe, Philip, 1733-1818 -- Correspondence; Malone, Edmond, 1741-1812 -- Correspondence; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; Macartney, George Macartney, Earl, 1737-1806 -- Correspondence; Burke, Edmund, 1729-1797 -- Correspondence
  - Letter to Sir Joshua Reynolds, at Leicester Square, 1790 October 18; Chambers, William, Sir, 1723-1796; 2 pages; 24 x 19 cm. (Box Reynolds 65)
    Written from Whitton Place. Concerning Sir William Chalmers.
    Correspondence; Chalmers, William, fl. 1798; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792 -- Correspondence; Chambers, William, Sir, 1723-1796 -- Correspondence
  - Letter to Sir Joshua Reynolds, circa 1790?; Chambers, William, Sir, 1723-1796; 1 page; 24 x 19 cm. (Box Reynolds 66)
    Complaining about expensive presents offered by Sir William Hamilton to the Royal Academy.
    Correspondence; Hamilton, William, 1751-1801; Royal Academy of Arts (Great Britain); Chambers, William, Sir, 1723-1796 -- Correspondence; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792 -- Correspondence
  - Collection of autograph drafts concerning his own collection of pictures, circa 1790?; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; 7 sheets; 37 x 22 cm, and smaller. (Box Reynolds 67)
  - Notes on the life of Sir Joshua Reynolds, containing an excerpt from a narrative by Anthony Pascin, circa 1800? (Box Reynolds 68)
    Creator unidentified.
    Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; Pascin, Anthony